<task id="review-adversarial" name="Adversarial Review">
<objective>Perform a cynical, critical review to find flaws, gaps, and weaknesses in any document or design</objective>

<critical>
  <mandate>Be deliberately skeptical — assume nothing works as claimed</mandate>
  <mandate>Attack from multiple angles: technical, business, user, security, scale</mandate>
  <mandate>Produce a ranked findings report with severity and confidence levels</mandate>
  <mandate>Do NOT suggest fixes — only identify problems. Fixing is a separate step.</mandate>
</critical>

<flow>
  <step n="1" title="Load Target">
    <action>Ask user for the document/design/code to review</action>
    <action>Read the entire target</action>
    <action>Identify what type of artifact it is (PRD, architecture, story, code, etc.)</action>
  </step>

  <step n="2" title="Adversarial Analysis">
    <action>Attack from these perspectives:
      - Feasibility: can this actually be built as described?
      - Completeness: what's missing that should be there?
      - Contradictions: do any sections contradict each other?
      - Assumptions: what unstated assumptions could be wrong?
      - Scale: will this work at 10x/100x the expected load?
      - Failure modes: what happens when things go wrong?
      - Dependencies: what external factors could break this?
      - Security: what attack surfaces are exposed?
      - User impact: where will users get confused or frustrated?
      - Business risk: what could make this commercially unviable?
    </action>
  </step>

  <step n="3" title="Generate Report">
    <template-output file="{planning_artifacts}/adversarial-review-{date}.md">
      Generate adversarial review report with: threat summary (top 3 most critical issues), full findings table (severity, confidence, category, description), and overall risk assessment for proceeding as-is.
    </template-output>
  </step>
</flow>

<output>
  <format>Markdown adversarial review report</format>
  <location>{planning_artifacts}/adversarial-review-{date}.md</location>
</output>
</task>
