<protocol name="review-gate-check">
<description>
  Shared protocol invoked by each review workflow after updating its Review Gate row.
  Checks if ALL reviews have passed and transitions story to done if so.
</description>
<critical>
  <mandate>The Review Gate table must have EXACTLY 6 rows: Code Review, QA Tests, Security Review, Test Automation, Test Review, Performance Review. No other rows are valid. If extra rows exist, remove them.</mandate>
</critical>
<step n="1" title="Read Review Gate">
  <action>Read the story file's Review Gate table</action>
  <action>If Review Gate section is missing: initialize it with EXACTLY 6 rows — Code Review (PENDING), QA Tests (PENDING), Security Review (PENDING), Test Automation (PENDING), Test Review (PENDING), Performance Review (PENDING). Do NOT add any other rows.</action>
  <action>If Review Gate table has extra rows beyond the 6 valid ones: remove the invalid rows</action>
  <action>Parse each row: Review name, Status (PENDING | PASSED | FAILED), Report link</action>
</step>
<step n="2" title="Evaluate Gate and Transition">
  <critical>
    <mandate>You MUST execute the transition even if the gate was already fully passed before this run. The purpose is to ensure story status matches gate state.</mandate>
    <mandate>Do NOT write to sprint-status.yaml from review workflows. Story file frontmatter is the source of truth. Sprint status is synced separately via /kratos-sprint-status.</mandate>
  </critical>
  <action>Check two things: (1) the Review Gate table rows, (2) the current story status</action>
  <action>If ALL 6 rows show PASSED AND story status is 'review': read the "Definition of Done" section — verify every item is checked (- [x]). If any item is unchecked: log "BLOCKED: DoD incomplete — {unchecked items}". Do NOT transition to done.</action>
  <action>If ALL 6 rows show PASSED AND all DoD items checked AND story status is 'review': change story status to 'done' in story file frontmatter ONLY. Do NOT write to sprint-status.yaml.</action>
  <action>If ALL 6 rows show PASSED AND the story status is already 'done': log "Story already done. No update needed."</action>
  <action>If any row is FAILED: log which reviews failed. Do not change story status.</action>
  <action>If any row is PENDING: log which reviews are still pending. Do not change story status.</action>
</step>
</protocol>
