<protocol name="review-gate-check">
<description>
  Shared protocol invoked by each review workflow after updating its Review Gate row.
  Checks if ALL reviews have passed and transitions story to done if so.
  Supports infrastructure review gate adaptations (ADR-022 §10.16.6):
  stories tracing to infra requirements (IR-/OR-/SR- prefixes) use adapted gate criteria.
</description>
<critical>
  <mandate>The Review Gate table must have EXACTLY 6 rows: Code Review, QA Tests, Security Review, Test Automation, Test Review, Performance Review. No other rows are valid. If extra rows exist, remove them.</mandate>
  <mandate>For infrastructure stories, 4 of 6 gates use adapted criteria. Code Review and Security Review remain unchanged for all story types.</mandate>
</critical>

<!-- Infra Review Gate Substitutions (FR-128, ADR-022 §10.16.6)
     When a story traces to infrastructure requirements, the following gate
     criteria are substituted. The gate row NAMES in the Review Gate table
     stay the same (for compatibility), but the review workflows apply
     infra-specific criteria instead of standard application criteria.

     | Standard Gate      | Infra Equivalent                    | Changed? |
     | Code Review        | IaC Code Review                     | Unchanged — same workflow, IaC expertise expected |
     | QA Tests           | Policy-as-Code Validation           | Checkov/tfsec/OPA pass replaces unit/integration test pass |
     | Security Review    | Security Review                     | Unchanged — critical for infrastructure |
     | Test Automation    | Plan Validation + Drift Checks      | terraform plan assertions replace automated test coverage |
     | Test Review        | Policy Review                       | OPA/Rego coverage replaces test quality review |
     | Performance Review | Cost Review + Scaling Validation    | Cost analysis and autoscaling validation replace load testing |
-->

<step n="1" title="Read Review Gate and Determine Gate Type">
  <action>Read the story file's Review Gate table</action>
  <action>If Review Gate section is missing: initialize it with EXACTLY 6 rows — Code Review (PENDING), QA Tests (PENDING), Security Review (PENDING), Test Automation (PENDING), Test Review (PENDING), Performance Review (PENDING). Do NOT add any other rows.</action>
  <action>If Review Gate table has extra rows beyond the 6 valid ones: remove the invalid rows</action>
  <action>Parse each row: Review name, Status (PENDING | PASSED | FAILED), Report link</action>

  <!-- Infra Gate Detection (FR-129): per-story gate type selection based on requirement ID prefix -->
  <action>Read the story file's YAML frontmatter traces_to field (e.g., traces_to: [IR-001, FR-128])</action>
  <action>Determine gate_type for this individual story by scanning its traces_to entries:
    - If ANY entry has an IR-, OR-, or SR- prefix → set gate_type = "infra"
    - If entries have only FR- or NFR- prefixes (or traces_to is empty/absent) → set gate_type = "standard"
    Each story is evaluated independently — in platform projects with mixed stories, each story gets the gate set matching its own requirement prefix, not a single gate set for the whole project.</action>
  <action if="gate_type == infra">Log: "Infra review gates detected for this story (traces to IR-/OR-/SR- requirements). Applying infrastructure gate criteria: QA Tests → Policy-as-Code Validation, Test Automation → Plan Validation + Drift Checks, Performance Review → Cost Review + Scaling Validation, Test Review → Policy Review. Code Review and Security Review remain unchanged."</action>
</step>

<step n="2" title="Evaluate Gate and Transition">
  <critical>
    <mandate>You MUST execute the transition even if the gate was already fully passed before this run. The purpose is to ensure story status matches gate state.</mandate>
    <mandate>Use the status-sync protocol to update story status — this ensures story file, sprint-status.yaml, and story-index.yaml stay in sync.</mandate>
  </critical>
  <action>Check two things: (1) the Review Gate table rows, (2) the current story status</action>
  <action>If ALL 6 rows show PASSED AND story status is 'review': read the "Definition of Done" section — verify every item is checked (- [x]). If any item is unchecked: log "BLOCKED: DoD incomplete — {unchecked items}". Do NOT transition to done.</action>
  <action>If ALL 6 rows show PASSED AND all DoD items checked AND story status is 'review':
    <invoke-protocol ref="status-sync" story_key="{story_key}" new_status="done" source_workflow="review-gate-check" />
  </action>
  <action>If ALL 6 rows show PASSED AND the story status is already 'done': log "Story already done. No update needed."</action>
  <action>If any row is FAILED: log which reviews failed. Do not change story status.</action>
  <action>If any row is PENDING: log which reviews are still pending. Do not change story status.</action>
</step>
</protocol>
