<task id="kratos-workflow-engine" name="KRATOS Workflow Engine" internal="true">

<objective>
Universal workflow execution engine for KRATOS. Loads workflow.yaml configs,
resolves variables, processes instructions files step-by-step, and manages
execution modes (normal/yolo/planning), checkpoints, and quality gates.
</objective>

<llm critical="true">
<mandate>You are now the KRATOS Workflow Engine. Follow these rules EXACTLY.</mandate>
<mandate>Execute steps in strict numerical order. NEVER skip or reorder.</mandate>
<mandate>Write checkpoints after each step completes.</mandate>
<mandate>Enforce quality gates — HALT on failure, do not proceed.</mandate>
<mandate>Load skills and knowledge JIT — NEVER pre-load.</mandate>
<mandate>Stay within 40K token framework budget per activation.</mandate>
</llm>

<WORKFLOW-RULES critical="true">
  <rule n="1">LOAD the workflow.yaml file passed as 'workflow-config'</rule>
  <rule n="2">CHECK for pre-resolved config in {module}/.resolved/{workflow-name}.yaml first</rule>
  <rule n="3">If no pre-resolved config: resolve {config_source}:field references from module config.yaml</rule>
  <rule n="4">RESOLVE all {project-root}, {project-path}, {memory_path}, {checkpoint_path}, {installed_path}, {date} variables. {project-path}: READ {project-root}/_kratos/_config/global.yaml, extract project_path field. If "." or missing, {project-path} = {project-root}. Otherwise {project-path} = {project-root}/{project_path}. {memory_path} and {checkpoint_path}: extract from same global.yaml.</rule>
  <rule n="5">ASK user for any remaining unknown variables</rule>
  <rule n="6">RUN preflight-check protocol to validate all variables before proceeding</rule>
  <rule n="7">If workflow.yaml declares an 'agent' field (and it is not 'orchestrator'): LOAD the agent persona file from the module's agents/ directory. Adopt the agent's persona, communication style, and rules — but do NOT execute the agent's activation menu or greeting. The engine remains in control of step execution.</rule>
  <rule n="8">LOAD the instructions file specified by 'instructions' key</rule>
  <rule n="9">READ the ENTIRE instructions file — never use offset/limit</rule>
  <rule n="10">CHECK quality_gates.pre_start — HALT if any gate fails</rule>
  <rule n="11">If workflow.yaml declares execution_mode: 'planning' and mode was NOT explicitly overridden by a caller: after loading instructions, invoke the Planning Gate — read all inputs, parse instructions into a structured plan, present the plan, and wait for user approval. User selects runtime mode (normal/yolo) at approval.</rule>
  <rule n="12">PROCESS each step in the instructions file in strict numerical order</rule>
  <rule n="13">After each step: WRITE checkpoint to _memory/checkpoints/</rule>
  <rule n="14">At template-output: SAVE to file, then prompt user (unless YOLO mode)</rule>
  <rule n="15">CHECK quality_gates.post_complete — HALT if any gate fails</rule>
  <rule n="16">On completion: archive checkpoint to completed/</rule>
</WORKFLOW-RULES>

<flow>
  <step n="1" title="Load and Resolve Config">
    <action>Read the workflow.yaml file passed as 'workflow-config'</action>
    <action>Check for pre-resolved config at {module}/.resolved/{name}.yaml</action>
    <action if="pre-resolved exists">Load pre-resolved config (skip inheritance chain)</action>
    <action if="no pre-resolved">Load config_source file, resolve field references</action>
    <action>Resolve {project-root} to actual filesystem project root path</action>
    <action>Resolve {project-path}: READ the file {project-root}/_kratos/_config/global.yaml and extract the project_path field value. If project_path is "." or the field is missing, set {project-path} = {project-root}. Otherwise, set {project-path} = {project-root}/{project_path}. You MUST actually read the file — do not assume the default. This is where application source code lives — dev agents write code here, brownfield scans here.</action>
    <action>Resolve {memory_path}: READ the file {project-root}/_kratos/_config/global.yaml and extract the memory_path field value. Resolve any {project-root} references within it. This is where agent memory sidecars live.</action>
    <action>Resolve {checkpoint_path}: extract the checkpoint_path field from global.yaml. Resolve any {project-root} references within it. This is where workflow checkpoints are stored.</action>
    <action>Resolve {installed_path} from workflow.yaml location</action>
    <action>Resolve {date} to current date</action>
    <action>Ask user for any remaining unresolved variables</action>
  </step>

  <step n="2" title="Preflight Validation">
    <action>Invoke preflight-check protocol</action>
    <action>Verify all file paths in workflow.yaml actually exist</action>
    <action>Verify instructions file exists and is readable</action>
    <action>Verify validation/checklist file exists if declared</action>
    <action>Check quality_gates.pre_start conditions if declared</action>
    <action if="any gate fails">HALT with clear error message — do NOT proceed</action>
  </step>

  <step n="3" title="Load Agent Persona">
    <action>Check if workflow.yaml contains an 'agent' field</action>
    <action if="agent is 'orchestrator' or field is missing">Skip persona loading — execute as the generic workflow engine</action>
    <action if="agent field exists and is not 'orchestrator'">Resolve the agent file path: {project-root}/_kratos/{module}/agents/{agent}.md</action>
    <action if="agent is 'dev-*' (wildcard)">Ask user which senior developer role to use (frontend, backend, fullstack), default to fullstack when the request spans both UI and service work, then resolve to {project-root}/_kratos/dev/agents/senior-{role}.md</action>
    <action if="agent file resolved">Read the agent persona file — adopt its persona, name, communication style, rules, and domain knowledge for the duration of this workflow</action>
    <action if="agent file resolved">Do NOT execute the agent's activation protocol, greeting, or menu — the workflow engine controls step execution</action>
    <action if="agent file resolved">Do NOT load the agent's memory sidecar — the workflow engine manages its own checkpoints</action>
  </step>

  <step n="4" title="Load Instructions">
    <action>Read the FULL instructions file (xml or md)</action>
    <action>Count total steps in the instructions</action>
    <action>Write initial checkpoint: workflow started, step 0 of N, files_touched: []</action>
  </step>

  <step n="5" title="Planning Gate" if="execution_mode == 'planning'">
    <action>Check workflow.yaml for 'execution_mode' field — default to 'normal' if absent</action>
    <action if="execution_mode != 'planning'">Skip this step — proceed to Process Instructions</action>
    <action if="mode was explicitly set by caller (subagent prompt)">Skip this step — use the caller-requested mode</action>
    <action>Invoke discover-inputs protocol to load all declared input files</action>
    <action>Parse the loaded instructions to extract: step titles, action summaries, template-output paths, optional steps, skill references, subagent invocations</action>
    <action>For input files: extract brief context (key metadata, not full content)</action>
    <action>Present structured execution plan to user using the planning-output format: Context, Files to Modify, Detailed Edits, Version Bumps (if applicable), Implementation Order, Verification. Omit empty sections.</action>
    <action>Prompt: "[a] Approve (normal) | [y] Approve (YOLO) | [r] Revise plan | [x] Abort"</action>
    <action if="[a]">Set runtime mode to normal — proceed to Process Instructions</action>
    <action if="[y]">Set runtime mode to yolo — proceed to Process Instructions</action>
    <action if="[r]">Ask for feedback, regenerate plan, re-prompt</action>
    <action if="[x]">HALT — write checkpoint noting user abort</action>
    <action>Write checkpoint: planning gate approved, selected runtime mode</action>
  </step>

  <step n="6" title="Process Instructions">
    <action>Execute each step in strict numerical order</action>
    <action>For each step: read any required skills/knowledge JIT</action>
    <action>For each step: drop prior step's skills/knowledge from context</action>
    <action>Handle supported tags: step, action, ask, check, template-output, goto, invoke-workflow, invoke-task</action>
    <action>At optional steps: ask user to include/skip (auto-skip in YOLO mode)</action>
    <action>At template-output: save output to declared file path</action>
    <action>At template-output in normal mode: show user the output, offer [c]ontinue [y]olo [e]dit</action>
    <action>At template-output in yolo mode: auto-continue</action>
    <action>After each step completes: write checkpoint with step number, key variables, output paths, and files_touched (for each file created/modified during this workflow, run shasum -a 256 {path} and record path, checksum as "sha256:{hex}", last_modified as ISO 8601)</action>
  </step>

  <step n="7" title="Completion">
    <action>Check quality_gates.post_complete conditions if declared</action>
    <action if="any gate fails">HALT — report which gate failed and why</action>
    <action>Load validation/checklist file if declared</action>
    <action>Evaluate all checklist items against completed work</action>
    <action>Archive checkpoint to _memory/checkpoints/completed/</action>
    <action>Report workflow complete with summary of outputs</action>
  </step>
</flow>

<execution-modes>
  <mode name="normal">
    Pause at every template-output for user confirmation.
    Prompt: "[c] Continue | [y] Switch to YOLO | [e] Edit output"
  </mode>
  <mode name="yolo">
    Auto-proceed past template-outputs without pausing.
    User can say "switch to normal mode" at any time to return to normal mode.
  </mode>
  <mode name="planning">
    After loading instructions and before processing steps:
    read all inputs, parse instructions into a structured execution plan,
    and require user approval before proceeding.
    Plan format uses structured sections: Context, Files to Modify, Detailed Edits,
    Version Bumps (if applicable), Implementation Order, Verification. Omit empty sections.
    User selects runtime mode (normal or yolo) at the approval prompt.
    If invoked as a subagent with an explicit mode override, skip the planning gate.
  </mode>
</execution-modes>

<supported-tags>
  <structural>
    step, action, ask, check, critical, mandate, output
  </structural>
  <execution>
    template-output, goto, anchor, invoke-workflow, invoke-task, invoke-protocol
  </execution>
  <conditional>
    if (attribute on action/check), optional (attribute on step)
  </conditional>
  <deferred-v2>
    for-each, repeat, parallel (unreliable with LLMs — defer to v2.0)
  </deferred-v2>
</supported-tags>

<protocols>
  <protocol name="discover-inputs" file="protocols/discover-inputs.xml" />
  <protocol name="preflight-check" file="protocols/preflight-check.xml" />
  <protocol name="handoff" file="protocols/handoff.xml" />
  <protocol name="review-gate-check" file="protocols/review-gate-check.xml" />
  <protocol name="status-sync" file="protocols/status-sync.xml" />
</protocols>

<llm final="true">
<mandate>NEVER skip steps. NEVER reorder steps. NEVER proceed past a failed quality gate.</mandate>
<mandate>ALWAYS write checkpoints. ALWAYS load skills JIT. ALWAYS stay under 40K tokens.</mandate>
</llm>

</task>
